Margaret Kimmel Records on Fred Rogers, 1973-2003 SC.1990.05
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Margaret Kimmel Records on Fred Rogers
1973-2003
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Kimmel, Margaret Mary
SC.1990.05
3 Linear Feet (6 manuscript boxes)
The Margaret Kimmel Records on Fred Rogers document Kimmel's work with the Mister Rogers' Archive, including the Mister Rogers' Neighborhood Collection and the OCLC project to catalog the media holdings. It also documents her work organizing and editing the book, Mr. Rogers Neighborhood: Children, Television, and Fred Rogers. In addition, the collection includes materials on other projects Kimmel was involved in, unrelated to Rogers.
Biography
Margaret Mary Kimmel was born on May 12, 1938 in Gary, Indiana. She earned her B.A. and M.L.S. from Dominican University in Illinois. Kimmel then worked as a librarian for the Enoch Pratt Free Library in Baltimore while also working as a freelance writer and teacher at various universities. Kimmel joined the University faculty in 1978 as an associate professor and earned her Ph.D. from the University of Pittsburgh's School of Information Sciences' in 1980. She attained the rank of professor in 1983. She directed the interdisciplinary program in children's literature undergraduate certificate program jointly run by the School of Education and the Dietrich School of Arts and Sciences. In 1983 she became a professor at Pitt and chaired the department of library science from 1990 to 1995, specializing in children's literature.
In addition to these positions, Kimmel also consulted for the television program, Mister Rogers' Neighborhood, and edited a books about Rogers' influence, titled Mister Rogers' Neighborhood: Children, Television, and Fred Rogers. Kimmel was also responsible for the Golden Triangle Books, a set of children's books taking place in Western Pennsylvania that she persuaded the University of Pittsburgh to reprint.
Scope and Content Notes
The Margaret Kimmel Records on Fred Rogers mostly contain materials that document her work organizing the Mister Rogers' Neighborhood Archives, which included the Mister Rogers' Neighborhood Collection and the OCLC project to catalog Mister Rogers' Neighborhood media, as well as editing the book, Mr. Rogers' Neighborhood: Children, Television, and Fred Rogers. A majority of the materials include grant proposals and applications, plannning materials, and correspondence.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically and consists of four series:
Series I. Mister Rogers' Neighborhood Archive
Series II. Mr. Rogers' Neighborhood: Children, Television, and Fred Rogers
Series III. Mr. Rogers Related Projects and Materials
Series IV: Projects, Events, and Committees, 1975-1999
Related Material
Mister Rogers' Neighborhood Collection, 1955-2003, SC.1989.07, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Margaret Hodges Papers, 1911-2006, SC.1990.03, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Elaine Lobl Konigsburg Papers, 1967-1986, SC.1986.01, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Rogers, Fred -- Performances; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Children's television programs; Mister Rogers' neighborhood (Television program); Rogers, Mister (Fred); Fred Rogers Company; Family Communications, Inc.; WQED (Television station: Pittsburgh, Pa.); Public Broadcasting Service (U.S.); Mister Rogers' neighborhood (Television program)
- Mister Rogers' Neighborhood Archive, 1973-1999; I.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials that document the Rogers' Archive Project, including the acquisition, donation, and organization of the Mister Rogers' Neighborhood archive and OCLC grant funded project to catalog episode tapes of MRN. Materials include correspondence, inventories, grant proposals, reports and related projects.
  - Correspondence, 1973-1984; 1.
    - Correspondence between Margaret Hodges and various stakeholders regarding donation of archives, 1973-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with Family Communications, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence in support of OCLC project, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence regarding cataloging of MRN tapes, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence and agreements for MRN puppets loaned to Children's Museum, 1984-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Inventories, 1985-1999; 2.
    - Inventory of materials at Family Communications, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Book purchases made to accompany Rogers' Archive, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Inventory of archival holdings, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Grants and Proposals, 1983-1987; 3.
    - Title II C Grant to strengthen holdings in the area of television and children, 1983-1997; 1.
      - Strengthening Research Library Resources Program, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Multiple editions of proposals and grant applications, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Personnel, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Planning and Budget, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Budget reports and correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Financial reports, grant reports, and final grant reviews, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - OCLC Project, 1980-1997; 2.
      - Proposal to Index Media, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Consultant OCLC recommendations, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - OCLC master keywords list (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - NEH grant proposal, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Various Grant Proposals, 1985-1997; 3.
      - Proposal for expansion of MRN archive, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - NHPRC grant proposal and application for preservation and storage of MRN archive, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Proposal and notes on storage and shelving (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Proposal and plan for Center for Research in Children's Television, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Proposal for organization of Family Communications information, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Proposal for development of Rogers' materials, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Mr. Rogers' Neighborhood: Children, Television, and Fred Rogers, 1989-1995; II.
  This series contains materials related to Kimmel organizing and co-editing, Mister Rogers' Neighborhood: Children, Television, and Fred Rogers, which was published in 1996 by the University of Pittsburgh Press.
  - Correspondence on books and with contributors, 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence on book and with contributors, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Forward: Born Again in Rogers by Bob Garfield (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Preface (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Fred Rogers and the Significance of Story by George Gerbner (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - What is Essential is Invisible to the Eye by Jeanne Marie Laskas (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Myth, the Man, the Legend by David Bianculli (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Reality of Make-Believe by Nancy E. Curry (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Fred's Shoes: The Meaning of Transitions in Mister Rogers' Neighborhood by Roderick Townley (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Musical Notes: An Interview with Yo Yo Ma by Eugenia Zukerman (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - With an Open Hand: Puppetry on Mister Rogers' Neighborhood by Susan Linn (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Mister Rogers: Keeper of the Dream by Paula Lawrence Wehmiller (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Mister Rogers Speaks to Parents by Ellen Galinsky (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Other Viewers, Other Rooms by Mary Rawson (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - A Neighborhood with Forest and Trees: Allies, Coalitions, Kids and Mister Rogers by Mark Shelton (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Afterward: A Nation of Neighborhoods by Marian Wright Edelman (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Typescript (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - Author biographies (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Bibliography typescript (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Mr. Rogers Related Projects and Materials, 1979-2003; III.
  - Public Library Association introduction of Fred Rogers (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence regarding Rogers' appointment as Adjunct Professor for the Information Science Library, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Photographs from MRN set, 1978-1987 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Press and articles on MRN and archives, 1978-1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Child and Story: A Symposium of Television (celebrating Rogers' thirtieth anniversary at WQED), 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Child and Story evaluations, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Projects and PR materials, 1985-1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Fred Rogers' Death, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - U.S. House of Representatives Honors, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Projects, Events, and Committees, 1975-1999; IV.
  This series contains materials related to various projects, committees, and events that Kimmel was involved in, not neccesarily related to Mister Rogers. This includes book projects, grants, awards, and talks.
  - Magic in the Mist, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Batchelder Award Committee, 1975-1984 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Batchelder interview, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - McElderry Award, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Nesbitt Room and Collection, 1977-1979 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "Before the Moving Van Arrives", article in School Library Journal, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Mass Media concentration at Pitt, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Beginning with Books, project development and expansion, 1984-1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Beginning with Books, cooperation with Family Communications, 1985-1989 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Beginning with Books, advisory board, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Margaret Hodges Day, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Alfred Summer, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - NEH Proposals, 1985-1993 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - E.L. Konigsburg Celebration, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Storytellers Unlimited, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Research on Margaret McElderry, 1989-1992 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Pittsburgh Magazine article on Kimmell, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Library outreach to public housing communities, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Generations Together, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Report on the organization of Family Communications information, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Curriculum development with Carnegie Mellon University, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 14)